<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  Dyer Geologist  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://www.scdyer.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  My personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://www.scdyer.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Launching my new static site  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://www.scdyer.com/posts/newsite/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://www.scdyer.com/posts/newsite/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Why I decided to go static  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  <p> 
<figure style="text-align:center;">
<img src=" /assets/atlin1.jpg" style="padding:0;width: 100%" alt=" A view of a valley before a mountain with pink flowers in the foreground" title=" "/>
<figcaption><i> The beautiful and remote Atlin region in northern BC</i></figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h1 id="launching_my_new_static_site">Launching my new static site</h1>
<p>After having spent too much money over the years on a Squarespace website that I hardly utilized, I decided it was time to simplify and downsize to a static website. Being a fan of the Julia programming language, I chose to use the Julia-based static site generator <a href="https://franklinjl.org/">Franklin.jl</a>. It has been a remarkably simple and enjoyable process, and while there are certainly many features I have not yet learned how to use, I am very pleased with the results.</p>
<p>Why did I decide to go static? I thought my previous website was very pretty. It opened to a page that cycled through several full page photos from field trips and field work that I have done during my schooling and research. The other pages on my site were nicely lain out with many high-res and beautiful photos of rocks, thin sections, or landscapes that I have taken over the years. It was certainly a nice website, but it was also a pain in the ass. Sure, the tools provided by Squarespace make it really easy to make pretty, nicely formatted layouts, but it added a level of complexity that made it extremely annoying to edit. It also meant I had to make a special layout when accessing it from a phone, or just live with an ugly mobile site. This all compounded to a website that I did not enjoy working on and that I was spending too much money on. Pretty pointless for a personal site to house my CV and information on my theses.</p>
<p>Over the years, as I have delved more into the world of tech, I have come to appreciate the simplicity of a static website. They are easy to use, easy to navigate, and easy to provide. I am hosting this site on GitHub and only pay &#36;20/year for the domain registration, and my site has pretty much all the same information it had on Squarespace. I found that building the site was straightforward and only required reading the docs and <em>some</em> technical know-how. Making modifications is quite easy as all the pages are written in Markdown and can be done directly in my text editor before deployment. The site is simple enough that I can dive into the HTML and CSS files and make modifications without too much fear despite knowing very little HTML or CSS. </p>
<p>This is all very enjoyable in ways that I never really imagined before, but I think I understand why I like it so much more than my Squarespace site. The fact that I am able to put this together myself and modify it to my liking all from my text editor provides a feeling of ownership that I never had with my previous site. If I want to make my site do something, I can actually figure out how to do it, so long as it&#39;s not anything too resource-intensive. If I want to move my site to another hosting service, I can do it very easily. I could even host it myself if I really wanted to.</p>
<p>This is a relatable feeling that I have to my bicycle, especially in comparison to how I used to feel about my car before I sold it. I used to drive a Honda Fit, it was a great car, very affordable but had great utility, but at the end of the day it was still a car and so maintenance was never cheap or easy. Since I am no mechanic, modifications were purely accessory such as adding a roof rack or a rearview camera and personal repairs never went beyond changing the battery. When I compare that to my bicycle, it&#39;s a very different relationship. Repairs are usually quite cheap, and I am often able to do the repairs myself. Modifications are straightforward and give me so much flexibility in making my bike look and feel the way I want it to. I can change the handlebars, the saddle, the wheels, the tires, the fork, the pedals, even the frame if I am so inclined and none of these modifications are particularly <em>challenging</em> to do. If I don&#39;t know how to do the repairs, they are usually very easy to learn, and if I don&#39;t have the tools, I can pop down to the local bike co-op to use theirs. While my bike will never go as fast as my car did, it takes me to most places I need to go, and it is truly mine in ways that my car never was. I think this is similar to the static website, while it is not as powerful as my old website, it takes me where I need to go, and I am able to take ownership over it in ways I never could before.</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Sabastien Dyer</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>